<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <div type="chapter" xml:id=""> <p> <seg n=""> <placeName ref="">DM, 21</placeName> </seg> </p> <p> <seg n="">Here is told of <placeName ref="">Greater Armenia</placeName></seg> </p> <p/> <p> <seg xml:id="c21_DM21_p1" n="1"><placeName ref="">Greater Armenia</placeName> is a large country. It begins at a city called <placeName ref="">Arzingan</placeName>, in which the best <term ref="">bukram</term> in the world is made; and there are many other handicrafts which cannot be told. There are also the best and finest spring-water <term ref="">baths</term> to be found in the world. </seg> <seg xml:id="c21_DM21_p2" n="2">The people are <persName ref="">Armenians</persName>, and they are subject to the <persName ref="">Tartar</persName>. </seg> <seg xml:id="c21_DM21_p3" n="3">There are many cities and towns. The most noble is<placeName ref=""> Arzingan</placeName>, which is the seat of an archbishop; the others are <placeName ref="">Erzurum</placeName> and <placeName ref="">Arzizi</placeName>. </seg> <seg xml:id="c21_DM21_p4" n="4">It is a very great province. And I tell you that in the summer the armies of the <persName ref="">Tartars of the Levant</persName> stay there, because in this province there is very good pasture for the cattle; but in winter they do not stay there for the very great cold of the snow, abundant beyond any measure; on account of which the cattle would not be able to live. </seg> <seg xml:id="c21_DM21_p5" n="5">In a village called <placeName ref="">Bayburt</placeName> there is an important <term ref="">silver</term> mine, and this village is found on the way from <placeName ref="">Trebizond</placeName> to <placeName ref="">Tabriz</placeName>. </seg> <seg xml:id="c21_DM21_p6" n="6">And I also tell you that in this <placeName ref="">Greater Armenia</placeName> there is <persName ref="">Noah</persName>’s ark, on a big mountain. </seg> <seg xml:id="c21_DM21_p7" n="7">In the south, towards the east, it borders on a kingdom called <placeName ref="">Mosul</placeName>, inhabited by <persName ref="">Christians</persName>, namely by <persName ref="">Jacobites</persName> and <persName ref="">Nestorians</persName>, of whom I shall tell you more afterwards; in the south, too, there are the lands of <placeName ref="">Muş</placeName><persName ref=""> </persName>and <placeName ref="">Mardin</placeName>, of which we shall speak afterwards, and many others, which it would be too long to recount. </seg> <seg xml:id="c21_DM21_p8" n="8">In the <term ref="">north</term> it borders on <placeName ref="">Georgia</placeName>, of which I shall tell you afterwards. </seg> <seg xml:id="c21_DM21_p9" n="9">And on this border towards <placeName ref="">Georgia</placeName> there is a fountain from which flows <term ref="">oil</term> in such great abundance that a hundred boats can be loaded with it at the same time; it is not good to eat, but it is good to burn and to rub on people and animals against mange; and people come from afar to this <term ref="">oil</term>, and the whole surrounding district does not burn other <term ref="">oil</term> but this. And it is good for many diseases. </seg> <seg xml:id="c21_DM21_p10" n="10">Now let us leave <placeName ref="">Greater Armenia</placeName> and we will tell you of the province of <placeName ref="">Georgia</placeName>. </seg> </p> <p/> </div> 